<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT xmlns="https://www.avpreserve.com/nunncenter/ohms" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="https://www.avpreserve.com/nunncenter/ohms/ohms.xsd"><record id="00043145" dt="2017-11-16"><version>5</version><date value="" format="yyyy-mm-dd"/><date_nonpreferred_format>Unknown Date</date_nonpreferred_format><cms_record_id></cms_record_id><title>Interview with Amichai Heppner</title><accession>RG-50.030*0094</accession><duration></duration><collection_id></collection_id><collection_name></collection_name><series_id></series_id><series_name></series_name><repository>Yale University Library</repository><funding></funding><repository_url /><file_name></file_name><sync></sync><sync_alt></sync_alt><transcript_alt_lang></transcript_alt_lang><translate>0</translate><media_id></media_id><media_url>https://yale.box.com/shared/static/5kvr7mlnmannn3p8vmd80oc86k4h34q5.m4a</media_url><mediafile><host>Other</host><host_account_id></host_account_id><host_player_id></host_player_id><host_clip_id></host_clip_id><clip_format>audio</clip_format></mediafile><kembed></kembed><language></language><index><point><time>78</time><title>Segment 1</title><title_alt></title_alt><partial_transcript>Question:  Good morning.  Would you please tell me your full name?

Answer:  Well, that's a difficult thing from the start because you know my full name has changed but my given name at birth was Max ________ Heppner.  

Question:  And where were you born?

Answer:  In Amsterdam in the Netherlands.

Question:  And what is the date of your birth?

Answer:  October 15th, 1933.

Question:  Can you tell me your parents' names and their occupations?

Answer:  Sure.  My dad's name was Albert Heppner.  He had no middle name.  He was by profession an art historian principally, although he did some writing and some some dealing.  A lot of art dealing.  And uh my mother's name was Irene Marian Kramer (ph) and uh she had no profession as far as training is concerned but since my father was a freelancer she did a lot of work with him. In fact my mom and dad worked together during all the time that I can remember before things broke down to the extent nobody was working anymore.

Question:  Did you have any brothers or sisters?

Answer:  No.  None.

Question:  Uh, were your grandparents living?

Answer:  Yes, my grandparents were living.  That is to say uh I I got to know and meet one from each side of the family.  Uh I knew my grandmother Dana (ph) who was my father's mother, and even better I knew my mother's father, whose name was Jacob Kramer and uh he lived with us. 

Question:  Could you tell me what your early childhood was like?

Answer:  Well, my early childhood was not unusual for an immigrant family.  Even though I was born in the Netherlands, I was barely born in the Netherlands.   My parents escaped from Berlin earlier the same year that I was born which was 1933.  And uh they settled in the Netherlands at at for them a very bad time.  It was the midst of a de...depression and uh they could barely escape with what little possessions they had.  They were relatively young married couple so they had a hard time economically and as I say they they worked together pretty well.  And my father stitched together little bit of this and a little bit of that so that they could make a living.  And so actually I was raised more by my grandfather in in that period of my life than by either parents and I liked my grandfather a whole lot better for that reason because since my father worked out of the home, why it was always shush here and shush there and don't touch and and make scarce.  And grandfather, Opa (ph) I called him, Opa Kramer, uh he took time.  He had the time.  He was retired so uh he dragged him around with him and really had more of an influence probably on my early education, preschool, than my parents.  I remember usually in the mornings, he would take me to the playground just to get away from being under foot at home and in the afternoon he'd take me to his pinochle game.  So the mornings he made like a child and in the afternoon I made like a grandparent and sat very quietly on the chairs.  I watched the old, old men, all refugees from Germany, play pinochle and drink tea and tell stories and that's how I grew up bilingual, at least bilingual.  Uh my father was in a in a very international type of of occupation and there were always people from all over coming to our house because that's, as I said, where my dad conducted his business.  Early in the morning already, my mother was an excellent hostess.  She made, was well-known for her breakfasts so people who came in on the morning train from Paris would come in and sit down at our at our table and and uh talk, chit chat, and talk business.  My father was an excellent linguist.  He was equally at home in German and in French and in Italian and in Dutch, and his English was quite good as well.  He has a classical education.  He spoke uh uh could could certainly read fluently Latin and Greek, so it it was a very actually lively I would say and international experience that I was exposed to.  So even though my father had a very strict rule because he was really upset that  uh the country that he loved so dearly, Germany, went for such for such crazy and criminal theories and activities as took place under Hitler.  He had a very strict rule.  No German.  Absolutely not.  They uh, my father went to to the trouble of translating German nursery rhymes and songs, children's songs  he didn't know any Dutch ones and I don't why he didn't take the trouble to learn.  Maybe that's hard for parents.  At any rate uh the way out that he choose was he kept uh the German songs and nursery rhymes and just translated them. And uh made my mother uh sing or recite the translations.  Which she did faithfully while he was around  but it was much easier for her to do it in the original German, and so I learned them both ways, and of course my grandfather didn't pay any attention to what made my father said about that and uh as soon as we were out of ear shot, that was the language he talked to me.  So as I say I was really raised bilingual and bicultural.  But that had to be subrosa because we had to hide it from my dad because the the outside effect that we were to give is that we were a Dutch family and uh he wanted to forget about ever having been German.</partial_transcript><partial_transcript_alt></partial_transcript_alt><synopsis></synopsis><synopsis_alt></synopsis_alt><keywords></keywords><keywords_alt></keywords_alt><subjects></subjects><subjects_alt></subjects_alt><gps></gps><gps_zoom>17</gps_zoom><gps_text></gps_text><gps_text_alt></gps_text_alt><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text><hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlink_text_alt></point><point><time>465</time><title>Segment 2</title><title_alt></title_alt><partial_transcript>Question:  Can you describe the changes in your family life and in the daily routine after the Nazis invaded the Netherlands but before you left Amsterdam?

Answer:  Yeah.  Well, of course, things went very much in stages.  I think a lot of people who've who've lived through that have have explained it pretty much the same way.  Uh the Germans, the Nazis, and it's hard to make that distinction, uh because the Nazis swept everyone along with them, uh the Germans when they invaded the Netherlands uh were an occupying power and in in the beginning made a real effort I think to kind of get the population on their side.  So uh our first reaction when we saw that Holland was uh going to be lost from the standpoint of of the fortunes of war, uh my father tried to pack up the family and we went, we jumped in a taxicab that he managed to secure somehow, and uh drove across the narrow neck of the northern part of the Netherlands to the harbor city of ____________, where uh we heard that they were sending refugee boats to pick up people, but we came just an hour too late maybe. At that time they were already blowing up the harbor installations and one of my earliest recollections is just seeing the whole harbor area of ______ go up in flames.  The reason that was so impressive is they had oil storage tanks there and uh of course that burned quite effectively  lots of fire, lots of smoke.  And uh a Dutch trooper at the edge of ______ turned us back and said it's too late and sent us back to Amsterdam.  And then we were really scared because we saw Amsterdam burning too but they were blowing up the oil storage tanks there too in the harbor and so uh once we got back things got fairly well back to normal  never completely because you know there was an occupying power in the street.  And again some of my earliest recollection is walking to school.  At the time we we Jewish kids were still going to the regular school.  There was no thought of of segregating us.  Uh but the Nazis one time just just for fun uh ran one of their uh uh personnel carriers up on the sidewalk just to watch the kids scurry.  So they they were very much uh an occupying power and then gradually started tightening the screws, obviously first a little tighter on the Jews and and uh but right behind it on the rest of the population until at the very end no one, Jewish or non-Jewish, escaped extreme depravation.  I mean the Jews were deported and gassed, but the rest of the people had a very hard time as well.  And uh after the war, you know, I I went back to the Netherlands for about a half a year, and one of the interesting, for me, things that I did was I joined a therapy group because I'm having a hard time living all this stuff down.  And I figured, in Dutch, on the scene, that might help me quite a bit.  And there were some people in there my age and when  raised that this was an issue for me, the subject completely switched from all the troubles they had at home and the troubles that they had at work, and they were completely there with me, talking about uh the experiences in the Netherlands, because no one came off free from it.  But you know the early experiences that I had for example is that the Nazis, the Germans  hard to hard to distinguish as I say  built a wall down the center of my school.  One side for the Jewish kids, one side for the non-Jewish kids.  And uh that was unusual.  Usually they picked one school for the Jews and another school for the non-Jews.  That that's how how it was dramatized that things were happening, things that were happening that segregated out the Jews and that I was one of them and that  I was in trouble.  
</partial_transcript><partial_transcript_alt></partial_transcript_alt><synopsis></synopsis><synopsis_alt></synopsis_alt><keywords></keywords><keywords_alt></keywords_alt><subjects></subjects><subjects_alt></subjects_alt><gps></gps><gps_zoom>17</gps_zoom><gps_text></gps_text><gps_text_alt></gps_text_alt><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text><hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlink_text_alt></point><point><time>724</time><title>Segment 3</title><title_alt></title_alt><partial_transcript>Question: Can you tell me a little bit about the events leading up to your departure from Amsterdam?

Answer:  Yeah.  Right.  Well, uh as I say, tightening the screws was done on my family in a very dramatic way in that uh they first pulled my dad's work permit so that my dad, who was very much in the public eye uh giving lectures at public museums, going to auctions and so forth, couldn't openly do that anymore.  So I uh I heard  it's hard to know  after all I was six, seven years old  it's hard to know what I remember and what I'm reconstructing from what people tell me  but I think I was very well aware that my father was uh having troubles with his business and where these troubles were coming from, that he had to do double bookkeeping and work out tricks with his friends so they could stay on in business and make it appear that he really was not.  Uh they actually came to raid our place several times.  First they came for silver and gold and the usual things that uh that they that they liked to steal, which was always done in very formal way, with receipts and stamps and all that sort of thing.  Uh and uh later on they came by stages to steal my dad's art collection which was his stock for for his dealership in in art, and I remember the first time they came around they they sent the Amsterdam police. Those people must have really been in a very you know almost untenable position because they didn't want to do this.  But they were made to do it and they had to work somehow and they were the police.  They were taken over.  So I remember when they came, my dad was out. He wasn't even supposed to be out of the city because he wasn't even allowed to ride public transportation anymore in those days.  So uh mother made up a story as to where he was, and uh the police did everything they do to to calm her down  they said don't worry about it uh, we don't even like to do this job but we have to do it, and they said if there is anything particular you'd like to do before we start our work, that's fine.  Now this was a hint to her that if she wanted to make one of those paintings that they knew were were around disappear, they wouldn't mind.  But you didn't know who you could trust, so here again I'm telling you part of what I remember, part of what I reconstruct  but I still remember my mother taking one of those paintings, a little one, and just letting her coat drop over it and see what would happen.  And they pretended like it wasn't there.   So gradually every time she'd pass through the house she she pushed that that painting further and further until she finally pushed it into a closet.  Then they came and listed everything on official forms and sealed it in the closet.  Put the seal of the city of Amsterdam on our on our hall  closet, and that was the end of my dad's stock.  Most of it they didn't get, but they got four or five good paintings which we've tried to in the interim to get back, unsuccessfully.  The stuff that we got back was all saved for us by friends and neighbors.  But uh the stuff that was confiscated, including my own bicycle, we never got back.  And how people can sit with wellknown pieces of art, because my dad dealt in good stuff, that they know is stolen, this very day is hard to believe. </partial_transcript><partial_transcript_alt></partial_transcript_alt><synopsis></synopsis><synopsis_alt></synopsis_alt><keywords></keywords><keywords_alt></keywords_alt><subjects></subjects><subjects_alt></subjects_alt><gps></gps><gps_zoom>17</gps_zoom><gps_text></gps_text><gps_text_alt></gps_text_alt><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text><hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlink_text_alt></point><point><time>937</time><title>Segment 4</title><title_alt></title_alt><partial_transcript>So you know the Holocaust goes on because people did not make restitution, not in a general way.  But the your question was what changed?  Well, uh what what changed then uh is that the action against property changed to action against people.  Now first they called up the the young folks and they told them, I remember I had a uh friend of the family that that played with me quite a bit.  Uh he was he was called up and he was glad to go because in the beginning it was not at all clear what was happening to people that were being called up for uh work related uh for war related work in Germany. They told these folks uh, come work for us a half a year and we'll let you go to Palestine. And so the kids were were anxious to go.  And they went willingly.  Sent letters back, sent letters back on a regular basis.   And when the letters stopped coming my parents knew.  They knew even though nobody ever really said this out loud.  So it was still a surprise the first day when they started picking up people in the street.  And my father ran into one of those uh street raids but fortunately he had a lot of friends and uh one of the stores that he was dealing with, one of the neighborhood stores, the storekeeper pulled him off the street and says you don't want to go there.  They're loading up Jews.  So he had he hid him behind the counter and then after after curfew the Germans set an eight o'clock curfew  on Jews in those days uh he slipped home and thought that that things were at least in the short run going to be better when they made a night raid on our block.  And uh my dad was trapped, because uh it was very clear that they were coming at us from all  sides, and uh that there was, that you couldn't just walk away from it.  So my dad decided to go out over the roof and you know one of one of the real uh high grabbing experiences that that I have to deal with is that I heard him discuss what some of the options were.  His friends came over because they were worried.   People took took risks.  They, Dutch people supported their Jewish friends, discussed what the options were, decided to go up over the roof.  I had been told over and over again, don't go on the roof.  And, but I knew just how to climb out the window and  get on the roof and I knew he was going to do that and try to escape over the roof and I was really worried.  Nobody said word one to me, except they suddenly noticed I was standing there.  Somebody grabbed me, pushed me in bed, pulled the covers over me even though I was protesting that I didn't put on my pajamas yet, and said you be quiet and you act like you're asleep.  And uh just about that time I heard the uh raiding parties stomp up the stairs.  They, they the the real Nazis did everything they did loud, so you could always tell when they were Nazis and Nazi sympathizers.  They would &quot;Hail Hitler&quot; real loud, and they had that opportunity cause we, unfortunately, had downstairs neighbors that were Nazi sympathizers.  When they saw those raiders coming in, they opened the door and spent a lot of time hailing and and shouting at each other in the hall, which was good cause it gave my dad extra time to get out.  Finally they stomped up the stairs, stomped on the door.  Finally one of my dad's friends let them in and quite innocently asked what they wanted, and although they screamed real loudly that they were looking for my dad and where was he and uh you know I heard my mother try to explain that she didn't know, maybe he had been picked up in the streets  she didn't know where my dad was.  And I heard them get madder and madder at my mom and finally tell her that they were taking her.  And uh so they did.  They barely gave her a chance to take her purse.  And uh they dragged her off and put her in one of their paddy wagons and hauled her off.  </partial_transcript><partial_transcript_alt></partial_transcript_alt><synopsis></synopsis><synopsis_alt></synopsis_alt><keywords></keywords><keywords_alt></keywords_alt><subjects></subjects><subjects_alt></subjects_alt><gps></gps><gps_zoom>17</gps_zoom><gps_text></gps_text><gps_text_alt></gps_text_alt><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text><hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlink_text_alt></point><point><time>1192</time><title>Segment 5</title><title_alt></title_alt><partial_transcript>Well, you said how, how did it happen then that you left town.  Well, uh things were formal and crazy at the same time.  There were rules for everything which were frequently broken and were up to the whim of which ever commander was in charge.  My mother was taken to a theater which was uh known as the Holland _________, uh which which later became known as the __________ because they they were no longer doing plays there.  They were using this as a concentration point for for people that they picked up, for for you know, for the shipment.  And uh while my mother was at this________, at this theater, uh she spotted a friend from across the street uh whose daughter was quite friendly with uh his name was Fritz Salten (ph), and Fritz was uh working for the Jewish Council to try and and get some comfort and and support for the people that had been arrested, detained or whatever word you want to use.  And uh my mother called him over and said hey uh Fritz, is there any way we, I I can get out of there.  And he said well, he says I know that your dad has done, well, she he would have said of course your husband, uh I know that your husband has done work for the Jewish Council.  They're letting people off sometimes uh that whose relatives worked for the Jewish Council.  Why don't you try that?  And so, uh through Fritz we we got a letter in the right format saying that my dad had done work as a teacher for the for the Jewish Council, and uh  _________was the was the famous commander, infamous commander of of that uh particular operation, let my mother go.  The only one he let go that day.  So that's why I say things were very arbitrary.  That day he decided to honor that particular rule.  So I mean my parents couldn't have it dramatized very much more uh extremely that it was time to get out of there, but where to go.  (Cough)  My my parents had one real close uh couple who were their friends whom they had asked already prelude to that time to kind of scout around a little bit and just find anything that might work to get us out of there.  And that was just in the beginning of some negotiation with with with them, very shadowy group uh who had had one front person by the name of _____________   drink a moment  whom Franz, that's the husband of that couple, had coincidentally just gone to see the very night that uh that they raided our place. They were unaware that we were being raided.  So they hurried up these negotiations and uh even though they seemed very haphazarded what apparently it would be is that uh they would, that this group then of adventurers would smuggle us south in a gasoline truck through Belgium, through France, up to a little enclave known as Free France uh which was kind of in between the uh occupied and nonoccupied areas of Europe, and which functioned as kind of a door, a lastminute door for people to escape. So in August of '42 when these events happened, uh we we left and went to the house of this Ari Hayward (ph), again to to see you know what what he could arrange to get us away further, so those were the circumstances that led to our leaving. </partial_transcript><partial_transcript_alt></partial_transcript_alt><synopsis></synopsis><synopsis_alt></synopsis_alt><keywords></keywords><keywords_alt></keywords_alt><subjects></subjects><subjects_alt></subjects_alt><gps></gps><gps_zoom>17</gps_zoom><gps_text></gps_text><gps_text_alt></gps_text_alt><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text><hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlink_text_alt></point><point><time>1429</time><title>Segment 6</title><title_alt></title_alt><partial_transcript>Question:   Would you tell me now from there on, the actual leaving and the events that followed after that?

Answer: Well, the hardest part I think for my parents in the leaving was that they had to leave my grandfather.  He was uh getting senile and diabetic and there was no question of making the run with him, so they left him in an oldage home and it was very hard for us to leave him.  Of course, they didn't tell me that we that we were going on the run.  They told me that we were going on vacation, which was credible since it was August, the big vacation month in Europe, and they said well, we're just going to go on vacation to this new friend of ours, Mr. Hayward, and uh you can play with his kids and uh and we hope we'll have a pretty good time.  Uh I didn't believe that but I also didn't have the nerve to ask what was really going on.  And you know, later on I've I've given a lot of thought to this. Do you tell your kids what goes on if it's if it's tough news?  And I've come to the conclusion that you do  at least you tell a tenyear old.  I was eight then.  You tell an eight year old because eight year olds understand a whole lot.  You don't need to tell them all the nitty gritty details, but you do need to tell them what's going on, because one of one of the most difficult things for me is the confusion. Hearing one thing and seeing another.  Knowing that my parents were telling me stories.  Don't want to say lies because they probably thought they were protecting me.  Certainly thought that they were protecting me.  But it was no protection. It was crazy making.  It was crazy making.</partial_transcript><partial_transcript_alt></partial_transcript_alt><synopsis></synopsis><synopsis_alt></synopsis_alt><keywords></keywords><keywords_alt></keywords_alt><subjects></subjects><subjects_alt></subjects_alt><gps></gps><gps_zoom>17</gps_zoom><gps_text></gps_text><gps_text_alt></gps_text_alt><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text><hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlink_text_alt></point><point><time>1534</time><title>Segment 7</title><title_alt></title_alt><partial_transcript>And we stayed uh with the the Haywards a couple of weeks until the Nazis raided the place, and they lost their nerve, and they didn't have any alternatives ready, so those were very difficult weeks from uh oh from mid-August to uh mid-September when uh we just wandered the countryside from one temporary shelter to another until we finally wound up in the bath house of a uh retreat center.  It sounds too fancy  it was just a little place out in the woods uh operated by a Catholic order and it uh was not being used for anything particular at the time  some some ________ came their from time to time to go swimming.  We ignored them.  They ignored us and we each pretended the others weren't there, but of course they knew.  And uh things were very unsettled.  There was still frequently a question of is the truck going to come, is the truck not going to come and uh what's to happen next because incredible as it may seem, we were having our meals catered at this retreat center.  It was very strange  uh about meal time we you would suddenly see a little boy appear in that clearing in the woods with a with a package of food for all of us.  And this boy that made the delivery was incredible because you know when you and I walk the woods you hear the leaves crackle and twigs crack didn't hear anything.  Suddenly the kid was there, and there was our food and then he would slink away and disappear.  Well, this was obviously not anything that could go on.  In fact one of the things that I remember is how extremely worried my dad was.  We were having beautiful September weather, unusual for the Netherlands  nice warm sunny afternoons where we could go swimming.  I mean it was great, in the swimming pool right uh we had to go swimming actually cause we at that time had only uh the clothes that that uh that we carried with us on our back because we were on the move so much and uh while Dad and I went swimming uh my mother and the lady in the other couple that was hiding with us, uh did the laundry in the other end of the swimming pool.  Uh but as I was starting to say, my dad was complaining about the good weather cause he says how long can this weather last.  When the cold weather comes, we'll freeze here.  There was of course no way to heat the bath house of a of a of a swimming pool and a remote camp.  So you know, when fall weather comes, particularly sunny weather, I find myself getting very uncomfortable and I have to remind myself  you know, that that harks back to these times and I'm only recently able to enjoy beautiful fall weather because I keep telling people the bad (ph) winter is going to come.  Now the the that is un a very bad position we were in because I, it was quite clear that these adventurers  we, we tend to want to see people in terms of good or bad but that doesn't always work.  These uh these people that Ari Hayward put us in contact with were good/bad.  They probably had some good motivations and uh from most of the stories that I hear about them repeated talk about how much money and when are you going to pay us and so on.</partial_transcript><partial_transcript_alt></partial_transcript_alt><synopsis></synopsis><synopsis_alt></synopsis_alt><keywords></keywords><keywords_alt></keywords_alt><subjects></subjects><subjects_alt></subjects_alt><gps></gps><gps_zoom>17</gps_zoom><gps_text></gps_text><gps_text_alt></gps_text_alt><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text><hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlink_text_alt></point><point><time>1756</time><title>Segment 8</title><title_alt></title_alt><partial_transcript>They were in it principally for the money.  And they were in a bad place because they couldn't deliver.  They had gotten their deposit  I am now reconstructing uh it's very clear that they had gotten their deposit but uh my father and and his friend uh Heinz Graumann who with also a wife and son was hiding along with us   I didn't trust him at all.  I didn't give him any more money than he could get away with.  I remember those discussions.  And uh it's amazing.  There's a Dutch proverb that says little pictures have big ears.  Uh this little picture had very big ears because I tried to find out as much as I could about what was going on because nobody was  going to be telling me anything at all.  Uh these people there, then these adventurers were in a bad way.  What were they going to do with us?  And as we know reconstructed, they decided to kill us.  It had a number of advantages.  First of all they knew that if the Germans got a hold of us they would do more, they would do worse than kill us, and secondly since they had already figured out where Heinz and my dad were were keeping their money, they could get paid instantly and not have to take any more risks with us.  So uh at the at that very time however the regular Dutch underground was starting to make some contact with that nebulous group of adventurers, and uh while they were exploring ways to get rid of us, they also explored a way of handing us over to the regular Dutch underground in that particular area of the Netherlands which was the southeastern corner, east of _______.  And uh ...so the story that they told us was that they had some people that maybe could help them and uh one by one they would they would uh which would which would be safer than herding a whole group of six people through the woods  one by one they would deliver us to these people, whereas at least a good portion of, at least two of these people were definitely decided on the murder route.  They uh took Michael, the the other boy that was hiding with us  uh he was considerably older than I, I was I was eight and he was probably around fifteen or sixteen at the time they took him first and they did in fact kill him.  And uh later on uh I was told they found graves that, shallow graves, that they had pre-dug for all us.  So they were really serious about doing us in.  But uh killing is hard.  People uh that talk about killing say uh your first killing really is the hardest.  When you see a a vibrant young boy that had just been laughing and joking with you and you suddenly split open his skull and you see his blood  that does something to people.  And from the testimony that uh came out in the trial afterwards, the person that uh swung the shovel that kill...killed Michael, came to trial after liberation.  It was clear that uh that the gruesomeness of of actually having done the act uh helped deter them from killing the rest of us, and then they tried the route of handing us over to the regular underground, which they did.</partial_transcript><partial_transcript_alt></partial_transcript_alt><synopsis></synopsis><synopsis_alt></synopsis_alt><keywords></keywords><keywords_alt></keywords_alt><subjects></subjects><subjects_alt></subjects_alt><gps></gps><gps_zoom>17</gps_zoom><gps_text></gps_text><gps_text_alt></gps_text_alt><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text><hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlink_text_alt></point><point><time>1961</time><title>Segment 9</title><title_alt></title_alt><partial_transcript>Question:  Alright.  After you were handed over to the underground, what happened then?

Answer:  Well, at at first we were still split up and uh my parents and I were brought to the house of uh Harry Janssen, Janssen we would say in Dutch, uh a smallscale farmer and professional thrasher who lived in the outback behind uh the village of Durna (ph) which as I say is east of ________ and uh he was uh loosely connected with the underground. The underground has to be loosely connected or else it doesn't function in occupied territories.  And uh that was an interim placement.  They were going to decide what to do next.  And uh to our surprise, after a while, the Graumanns showed up there too, because the people that were supposed to have taken them in didn't and the last time we saw the members of this nebulous group of adventurers that I talked about was when they delivered the Graumanns.  Said they would come back for them and never did.  And uh all the connections that were supposed to have worked for Harry to to get us away or out of the country or whatever, didn't work.  So he inherited us.  And although he never expected to be hiding five Jews for any length of time, he did.  And I think the relationship immediately became quite close because of course in the beginning, no one knew what had become of Michael.  And uh Harry could see Elli Graumann, Michael's mother, wilting more and more each day, not knowing what had happened to her son.  So he he uh he started the underground into a manhunt.  And they combed the place till they finally found one of the people of what I have been calling that nebulous group, and they nabbed himand interrogated him till they, till he told the truth, and showed where where Michael was buried.  So that dramatized to Harry you know the the type of pickle that we were in, and I guess kind of gradually at first, week by week, he decided to to become the person to to shelter us, take charge of us.  And he did that.</partial_transcript><partial_transcript_alt></partial_transcript_alt><synopsis></synopsis><synopsis_alt></synopsis_alt><keywords></keywords><keywords_alt></keywords_alt><subjects></subjects><subjects_alt></subjects_alt><gps></gps><gps_zoom>17</gps_zoom><gps_text></gps_text><gps_text_alt></gps_text_alt><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text><hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlink_text_alt></point><point><time>2127</time><title>Segment 10</title><title_alt></title_alt><partial_transcript>He did this two years almost to the day till we were liberated, despite raids, despite searches specifically of his place, despite interrogation, this man was a master at dissimilation and withstanding uh interrogation.  He could make up stories.  He was a natural raconteur.  We kids loved him because he could tell us kids stories too.  A marvelous storyteller. That came in very handy for him, cause he'd make up some story and it always worked.  Like one time I remember there was a search specifically of his place.  They came to  he he had his contacts and he had been warned uh that there would be a search of his place.  And I I had the measles.  I was really sick.  And you know we had various places that we would hide out when the word came that there'd be a search, but there was no question it would have been inhumane to stick me into one of these places so he stuck two of his kids uh about the same age in bed with me  it was obvi...it was quite common in poor uh families for several kids to sleep together, but that was not the usual way that I slept.  And the other two kids had the measles too I think, and so they they stuck them, he stuck them, all three of us, in in one of the bedrooms, and put a big sign on the door, &quot;Quarantined&quot;, and so when the search party came through, he says feel free to look anyplace.  I've got nothing to hide he says, but don't go in there.  I've got some really sick kids in there, and the doctor put a sign on there &quot;quarantined.&quot;  I don't want you guys to get sick.  So well after they made a perfunctory look inside and they say three real sick kids in there, threw the door closed, and uh you know, he got us through just by talk.  And even though he had some very very good places that he tried at various place, at various times to hide us, the most interesting one was a double wall.  In order to picture how the double wall functioned, you have to you have to picture a very primitive farmstead, and the farmsteads in in Holland uh from an earlier era like this one dated from, had the animals and the people under one roof.  The people would live up front, and the animals would be in the back.  Very convenient if you go milking cause you just open up a door and you're in the stable and you can milk the cows and bring the milk right into the kitchen.  In fact that's what they did.  Well, in this wall, they had they had two walls then one separating the house from the main part of the stable and then another separation between the cows and the horses.  And that's where they built the double wall.  And he had a friend, a uh a bricklayer come in, and duplicate the the wall that was already there exactly as it was uh oh about maybe uh a couple of feet away, and uh then to get to that place they would hoist us up to the rafters and let us down with a rope so that we'd between the two walls and of course there was no door. </partial_transcript><partial_transcript_alt></partial_transcript_alt><synopsis></synopsis><synopsis_alt></synopsis_alt><keywords></keywords><keywords_alt></keywords_alt><subjects></subjects><subjects_alt></subjects_alt><gps></gps><gps_zoom>17</gps_zoom><gps_text></gps_text><gps_text_alt></gps_text_alt><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text><hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlink_text_alt></point><point><time>2329</time><title>Segment 11</title><title_alt></title_alt><partial_transcript>Uh these raids always came at the worst times.  I remember one time my mother, my mother had a severe case of diarrhea when the alarms came and they hoisted her in there with uh with uh a potty and uh can you imagine those poor people that had to sit there for I think twenty-four hours with someone who had an over-flowing potty of diarrhea.  Ugh. Fortunately they hid me someplace else that time.  They hid me in a haystack.

Question:  Tell me a little bit about your daily routine when you were living with the farm family.

Answer:  Well, I think I think everybody was quite aware that in order to go, to keep from going stircrazy, you have to keep people busy.  And uh the Janssens increasingly gave us work to do.  We peeled all their potatoes, and when I say all, potatoes was a staple and uh the Janssens were sheltering not only Jews but at various times various members of their rather extensive family that had moved to the city and were running out of food. So there was uh one other chicken house full of people.  Uh Harry used to say how fortunate that the Nazis stole all our chickens. This way we can house the people.  We can house the refugees. There's another chicken house full and sometimes some of the other buildings.  I had relatives in them too.  So we strung the beans and peeled the potatoes.  Something that uh people find hard to believe  we strung tobacco and Holland is not known as a tobacco raising country, but uh you know, we were talking a little earlier how starved people were for for these cigarettes or anything resembling cigarettes, so they found some variety that would grow there and people took tremendous risks smuggling uh seeds for tobacco which we then grew secretly and strung secretly.  There was a lot of secret stuff.  I still remember Harry did another thing which was strictly illegal.  He butchered.  Uh he butchered hogs.  And we, and people who farmedwere supposed to deliver all uh animals that were ready for market, all produce to the Germans, which they then shipped east.  They didn't give hardly anything to the people in the Netherlands, which is why there was such a famine there.  But uh Harry in contravention of all the rules, slaughtered, and we did that right on the kitchen floor.  Uh can imagine a little Jewish boy...(laughter)...a scene like that.  I had no real sense of where meat was coming from and to see then slit the throat of a hog and string it up from the ceiling and cut it up into pieces and make sausage out of the guts   that was some experience. But uh it was something that the kids all watched with glee and uh I made a real effort to to fit in.</partial_transcript><partial_transcript_alt></partial_transcript_alt><synopsis></synopsis><synopsis_alt></synopsis_alt><keywords></keywords><keywords_alt></keywords_alt><subjects></subjects><subjects_alt></subjects_alt><gps></gps><gps_zoom>17</gps_zoom><gps_text></gps_text><gps_text_alt></gps_text_alt><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text><hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlink_text_alt></point><point><time>2518</time><title>Segment 12</title><title_alt></title_alt><partial_transcript>It was hard because you know I was uh a city slicker from the north and they were country bumpkins from the south and they, they not only had a completely different culture, they had a different language. They spoke Dutch but it was such a different dialect that uh if they talked among themselves I couldn't understand a word they were saying.  And I knew I was I was a native Dutchman.  However fortunately they learned standard Dutch  in school so if they wanted to they could include me.  And of course in short order I learned the dialect and learned to watch  such things as hog slaughter.  And it was uh kind of a fun thing  in a way because the one thing that uh we kids would get out of it immediately was the bladder.  And you will say, what do you do with a hog bladder.  Well, what you do is you you try to scrape and wash it clean the best you can, and then you take an old tin can and you tie the top of the bladder to the tin can much as you  would make a drum, with one difference. You'd also take a stick and you would tie that to the center of the bladder, centered over the drum, centered over the over the tin can, and then you would tie it taught.  Then you would spit into your hands, _____, and then you would slide it up and down the stick and that was an instrument, an instrument which everybody learned to hate.  But uh for uh for uh, what what is this holiday called in English  sometimes it's it's hard to translate on the spot  uh it's it's a spring holiday just befo...just before the frost (ph)  uh, help me, it's fat fat Monday in French.  Mardi Gras. OK.  Uh on Mardi Gras we would go out and uh and serenade the neighbors which with what we called the _________, and uh as much to get rid the awful noise as anything else, they would they would give little handouts and then the kids would troop other places.  Well, of course I couldn't do this during the occupation but I was there a good while after and uh I remember doing that with the kids and of course I had the fun of of making my own _______.  Well, what else did we do?  Well the interesting part is that unschooled and unlettered as the Janssen's were, uh especially the older girls got quite interested in all the literary activity of the Ph.D.'s that uh were in hiding with them.  Now these Ph.D. uh parental generation of mine was was odd from from my retrospective point of view.  They were dressed like you and I are today, in three-piece suits and tie, on a farm in the outback where there was no pavement within miles.  Where there was mud all around, where they had to make fire in stoves with wet peat that filled the place with acrid smoke in every morning.   That was my dad's job and uh he was he was extremely allergic.  He had uh he had a mild case of asthma and and lots of associated allergies and was the worst possible job but Heinz never could learn how to light a fire, so that was my dad's job which he did in his three-piece suit and tie, every morning.  That went on first.  Uh so that showed the kind of activity  you asked activity  uh it is amazing the p...these two Ph.D.'s had their literary material shipped in on on the underground.</partial_transcript><partial_transcript_alt></partial_transcript_alt><synopsis></synopsis><synopsis_alt></synopsis_alt><keywords></keywords><keywords_alt></keywords_alt><subjects></subjects><subjects_alt></subjects_alt><gps></gps><gps_zoom>17</gps_zoom><gps_text></gps_text><gps_text_alt></gps_text_alt><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text><hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlink_text_alt></point><point><time>2761</time><title>Segment 13</title><title_alt></title_alt><partial_transcript>Uh my father had a connection in Amsterdam.  One of his students, a very advanced student of art history, uh collaborated with him in the writing.  He did uh the research work in the libraries uh which he which he would either copy or summarize and send send down, and my dad would would write in his field.  And uh he had a portable typewriter, so big we still have it today  a little Hermes (ph), a baby Hermes that uh he picked up in Switzerland and it still works today.  My mother uses it today and has used it all this time.  Tremendous advertising I would think for that firm.  Well, in that outback place they had a typewriter.  Uh Heinz who had different interests uh decided to do a history on the life of Millieure (ph), the playwright because to the underground he he got uh in contact with a group of monks across the border in Belgium, in the southeast corner of the Netherlands, very close to Belgium uh who unbeknownst I guess to to the uh uh regular scholars had hoarded away the personal papers of Millieure which they smuggled to Heinz and which he made a treatise out of.  He finally wrote a play on the life of Millieure so that's what went on in that chicken house, as hard as it is to believe.  Well, with all this literary activities the kids came by to see and my father started uh teaching them uh how to do poetry and how to make drawings and we made skits.  I remember one of the neighbors who knew  most neighbors knew uh that Harry was hiding refugees  was having a fiftieth wedding anniversary and we made the most elaborate uh skit for them, uh a whole production uh uh weaving together stories from from the families that were going to be at this uh at this at the ceremony, at the celebration.  And I still have those today.  Very good stuff.  And uh so it it made a very nice uh contact between uh people who otherwise would have been semiliterate.  Uh there are members of the family who who didn't join in this.   ____ is you know barely literate even today.  Uh their their letters take a genius like myself to decipher but uh we became very good friends which is from what I hear a rather unusual story because relations between people who were hiding and people who were hiding them were not always the best.  You can imagine what tremendous pressure that put on people and uh the Janssens did extremely well not only in successfully hiding the five people in their charge for for uh two years and then taking care of them afterwards, because afterwards we had no place to go.  We were in the part of the Netherlands that was liberated half a year befo...before the rest.  We were fortunate in that respect.  So even while we lived in the war zone for a half a year they continued to take care of us.  In the beginning we had money to pay them, but I I find in going through the uh uh documents we have from this time that uh shortly after liberation we ran out of money, and food was even scarcer then if possible than before.  Harry continued to feed us and uh Dad wrote him an I.O.U. and I have the I.O.U. that he crossed out uh because he decided to forgive the debt.  So that was uh the kind of relationship we had with the people.</partial_transcript><partial_transcript_alt></partial_transcript_alt><synopsis></synopsis><synopsis_alt></synopsis_alt><keywords></keywords><keywords_alt></keywords_alt><subjects></subjects><subjects_alt></subjects_alt><gps></gps><gps_zoom>17</gps_zoom><gps_text></gps_text><gps_text_alt></gps_text_alt><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text><hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlink_text_alt></point><point><time>3010</time><title>Segment 14</title><title_alt></title_alt><partial_transcript>Question:  Did your, did you get into a routine for for studies?

Answer: Yeah.  I personally had such a routine where there were at least two or three hours every morning that uh we had subjects that I didn't particularly like and that I don't think my dad was all that interested in either.  He was a very literary person.  Math and and sciences were not his strong points, so that's what we saved for the morning.  But the fun part, the composition, the drawings, the language studies and don't forget geography geography was the overriding interest because you know that's where our salvation was to come from in a literary in the literal sense, so we we traced the Allied troop movement over every inch of North Africa and through Italy and through France until they finally came through Belgium to liberate us, so I I you probably remember when uh the Allied troops first landed in in uh western France they they came to Normandy and were stuck there, and I still know all the little hick town villages like _____ in Normandy where these battles were fought because uh they were all recreated in my atlas that I still have today. 

Question:  What were some of the hiding places that were used for you and your family and the other refugees when for example there was a raid?

Answer:  Well, I've mentioned the principle one.  Uh we we uh, the first one where we were the least prepared, Harry took us way back into the peat bog where he knew of an abandoned barn where we hid in hid in the attic. Uh after that as I told you he constructed or had constructed this double wall.  For a time they they toyed with the idea of building an air raid shelter with uh with a secret room in this, but even though the air raid shelter got partly built that that never came came up.  One time they tried digging a tunnel under a haystack for me.  That was special for me because it couldn't be uh so big that other that other people bigger than a nineyear old that I was at the time would fit in.  You couldn't hide in the haystack because it became known pretty quick that when they did a raid they always ran uh sabers and bayonets through haystacks.  If they came up with blood they knew they caught somebody.  So, but under the haystack was the variation that was the worst night I think I ever spent in hiding.  That was awful, in the cold clammy dark place under that haystack.  Uh I complained very little, but they never did that again because I I did complain and that was really awful.  Uh other times when there was little advanced notice we would just hide in the ditches and plenty of ditches to hide in in the Netherlands and uh in a dry, in the drier season that gives you quite a bit of cover and mobility cause if you can get some sense of which way the raid is going you can constantly keep cover and and keep on the move.</partial_transcript><partial_transcript_alt></partial_transcript_alt><synopsis></synopsis><synopsis_alt></synopsis_alt><keywords></keywords><keywords_alt></keywords_alt><subjects></subjects><subjects_alt></subjects_alt><gps></gps><gps_zoom>17</gps_zoom><gps_text></gps_text><gps_text_alt></gps_text_alt><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text><hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlink_text_alt></point><point><time>3215</time><title>Segment 15</title><title_alt></title_alt><partial_transcript>Question:  Were the raids frequent?

Answer:  Well, uh I am reconstructing that there must have been four that actually reached the place and maybe three or four others in the neighborhood which were just as bad from the standpoint of getting everybody all excited because you never knew are they going to come to your farm or not, but uh there was a Nazi sympathizer unfortunately that uh lived across the street.  Again it's hard to say.  You know, as I told you before, it's hard to tell the good guys from the bad guys.  Uh my hunch is uh that this fellow like like many people who who played with the Nazis was more interested in being important than being disloyal and uh you know, an occupying force, especially a loud and oppressive one, has a certain amount of attraction to it, and uh there was an element, there's a type of of a personality I think that gets attracted to this and wants to go over to them and and tell them something that they don't already know, and get pat on the back and be told you're a great citizen and great supporter of the new order.  Uh and uh it is pretty clear that uh that the that the neighbor across the street told on us which is breaking ranks with with all the rest of the people around who who did know.  And uh after liberation Harry really confronted this guy according to what uh his wife Nina (ph) told me later, until he had this guy on his knees in the middle of the street begging for mercy.  I mean there were that kind of strong feelings about but uh that is how come there were specific raids on our place.  I mean there were there were really actual fingers pointed at Harry and that he was able to keep cool under those circumstances.  One day he payed played cards to, in the first raid as a matter of fact, he carried off by playing cards.  He and his friend Marinus (ph) who were who was his closest friend and who was in the underground with him, uh had gotten notice that uh that we were going to be raided with very little advanced notice.  Took us out to this barn in the outback like I told you, and then he and Marinus uh uh got together some drinks and uh spread the card, cards out you know moments before the raiding party came.  They they acted like they had been playing and drinking all night, acting completely surprised.  What you guys looking here on a on a strange night like this?  Well, we were told to make a search.  Search for what?  Well, you know, that conversation went on like that till they got them into the game where where these two excellent card players first took all their money.  To keep interest in it, they let them win some of it back, which you know ate up a whole lot of time, all the time saying oh there's always time to go looking around the place, till they were so drunk and so tired that uh they hardly did any looking around at all.  And Harry kept the best uh the best drinks for occasions like this.  So he he played his way through a search which is probably also weird in the annals of uh secret operations.

Question:  We'll pause here for a moment to change the tape.</partial_transcript><partial_transcript_alt></partial_transcript_alt><synopsis></synopsis><synopsis_alt></synopsis_alt><keywords></keywords><keywords_alt></keywords_alt><subjects></subjects><subjects_alt></subjects_alt><gps></gps><gps_zoom>17</gps_zoom><gps_text></gps_text><gps_text_alt></gps_text_alt><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text><hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlink_text_alt></point></index><type></type><description></description><rel /><transcript></transcript><transcript_alt></transcript_alt><rights></rights><fmt>audio</fmt><usage></usage><userestrict>0</userestrict><xmllocation></xmllocation><xmlfilename></xmlfilename><collection_link></collection_link><series_link></series_link></record></ROOT>